ok so where where where is your head at
I'm not really sure but maybe now you have a
sense of okay I kinda get what
programming is
I've gotta write instructions with a
specific syntax
and I could choose all these different
languages and all these different
environments for different kinds of
applications and
for different operating system and for
different hardware but here
we're going to use processing what
advantages does
processing give us what kinds of things
can we make with processing what is the
lens that we're gonna look through
to learn the fundamental concepts a
programming this is key
we're not I'm not it's not my intention
here for you
to learn processing it's my intention
for you to learn
the fundamental tools of computation
we're going to use processing as the
environment to learn those tools
but those tools those concepts will go
across
any programming language environment
that you choose to use in the future
so why- as I said processing we- it's a thing
we download
we can open it- one of the first things
you might do yourself
and I'll kinda do this for you is take a
look through the examples
so you can see here there's a little
window that you can pop up that has
examples
and you can kinda look through look
these basics and some of these basic things
will give you a sense of
what is processing doing. you can learn about
color, you can learn about form, you can learn
about math
so if for example I just go here and
lets say we wanna learn about hue
with processing I can run this
particular example
and you can see that what it's doing
here is as I move the mouse back and
forth across the screen
its changing the hue of the color that
I'm drawing
so there's a range of examples and you'll
notice these examples, generally speaking
have a visual design component so
if you're interested in design, animation,
images, creative applications of
software,
processing is a good environment to
explore ideas in that area
Umm another thing and I'm just
gonna kinda give you a quick range
as you look through you might start to
look through a lot the examples under
topics:
and one of the ones that's sure dear to
my heart that you might look at is OK
simulate so there's a lot of nice
examples we can look at
this idea on what- of simulating
physics elements through processing you can see there are
some circles on the screen
as I click them and move them with the
house- my head is always- clearly this is very
poorly
what I'm doing here. Umm they there they
have this
spring-like motion so one of the nice
things about processing is there's a-
when you downloaded it, there's a wide range
examples and to get a sense of
what can I do, what are some ideas of
things I might try to make: you could
you could spend a whole day just
clicking through and running all of the
examples
Umm the other thing that I would just
mention is that processing
has a in addition to the sort of 2d drawing
engine which allows you to draw
simple and and kinda complex shapes and
animations in 2d
you can do a lot of stuff in three
dimensions as well
I guess I'll just open up this one
called Planets
and we can see here's a nice- Whoo this is
beautiful! I'm going to have to use this
for something,
but here we can see, err this err, nice
little demonstration of how you can do
3d rendering in processing as well
err
and you can see err, you can do err-err, all sorts of
different kinds of
camera stuff, lighting stuff, textures: all
things that you might find in a 3d computer graphics environment
that' what you can do
and you can do with the processing
environment as well so
this is- I just closed everything
that is the examples- the other thing, it's
just something else I really want to
mention about processing
so okay so here's something I kinda should
have might have wanted to mention, we
have this
a show like crazy list of all these
programming languages that I was kinda
saying aaah,
okay, so here we're using processing and
one thing you might think it's like
oh is it just
processing, it like this toy environment
that I can kind of just do a little like experimental
ideas in buit  can't really make
a a large-scale projects with; so one of
the things that I like about processing is
both its ability to allow you to
get started very quickly and learn the
basics but also you can build fairly
large scale sophisticated projects in it
and one of the reasons for this is, is that you
aren't learning the processing language-
yes you're using the oppressing environment
yes there is a a set of processing
functions
that are that are that are needed for
processing itself but really the language a
that you're writing
code in is Java, now Java is probably about right
now, and I refer to the era that we live in,
2013, it's probably like the least cool
thing you can learn like
it's much cooler to learn JavaScript or
ruby and and there's lots of great stuff
you can do; i mean
javascript is especially on the web
now and, erm canvas and webGL
all this amazing stuff that I also encourage
you to learn but
there is an advantage to using Java or
the fact that processing is built on top of
Java, er, you know Java is kinda
in many ways I i've heard this said
about Java err
something silly, but, it's not the best
language for anything but it does
everything, so if there's anything you're
thinking about doing if you are you wanna
like read your
email into your processing program and
then draw little bubbles on the screen
for every email you've received
or you want to connect to the Microsoft
Kinect
or you want to use err this physical
piece of this hardware you want to use the
sensor
erm, you can really do just about anything
you'll find a java library out there
for just about anything so processing
because it's built on Java
is incredibly extendable through
libraries
now what are these libraries and you can
see I'm into
if I go back to that examples window erm,
looking through those examples
topics I could go down to start to look at
libraries
one which i'll just demonstrate really
briefly to you right now is video
so under capturei'm gonna look at er, one of these
examples; gonna run this mirror example
and I think this will work
err, its effect we should edit
it's taking a minute or so here we can
see a look what's interesting is this is
a green screen so you can see the green
wall in the actual camera
so the camera here is reading my image
so processing can connect to pieces of
hardware through libraries, can connect to
your camera
and what this example is doing is it's
taking every single pixel from a regular
good old-fashioned image
and instead of drawing that pixel as a
a a- drawing that pixel as a rectangle on
the screen rotated according to the
brightness or something
so you can see that we can create this
abstract visualization of the data
the color data that's coming in from a
camera this is, err, something we'll
explore in great detail
in a future video how to write these
kinda examples how to capture images
how to read pixels, how to draw stuff based on
those pixels; so
be- the video library is something that
comes with processing when you download it
but  processing itself has a huge, has a
large community of people making
libraries and I downloaded one an
arbitrary one
called the Yahoo weather library we can
tell, just open up this example
erm, this library allows you to connect
to Yahoo- Yahoo weather data
and you can see here that this processing
sketch
has grabbed the weather information from
the city of berlin, it's fair, the wind
direction is three
10 which must maybe is a err, angle!
and, erm, and the wind speed is a eight
kilometers kilo-
kilometers- I became French, so
kilometers per hour
so you can see then this others these
particles these dots that are drawn on the screen
that are moving according to that wind
direction: so
connecting to data sources there if you
have an idea for something and processing
doesn't do it
if you can write the Java code for that
you can make it into a library and you
can do it in processing so
the processing is tremendously extendable
through all sorts of libraries, if you want to get a
sense
up what the available libraries are for
you, er,
if we go back to the processing website
waa- and go to libraries
you can see there is a nice list of tons
and tons
libraries and you can also get them,
which I-I- this is err,
through, err, through this library
manager that comes with
processing software itself so we can go
through this list of
libraries and if I want this library
which is
a lightweight library for creating
animations and trans-
transitions I can click Install and it will
install that library I can use it
in my code- okay! so this is kinda
at least a little bit of, erm, me getting
started showing you-
okay! here's the process development
environment. here are
some the examples, here some libraries, here's
the kind of things that can do
and next thing I wanna kinda briefly
look at is just a quick range of some
projects
that have been made with processing to
get you thinking about
looking at erm, larger-scale
installations and animations and and
things that people are doing
the first project I'm going to show you
what's called Chronograph by Casey Reas, one of the
creators of processing and
Tal Rosner, I apologize if I've
pronounced the name
here incorrectly, erm, this is a project
which I'll skip to the end
here to just show you this
time-lapse. you can see this is a projection
piece
that's projected onto the side of this
building which is
New World Center in Miami Florida for
the New World Symphony so
this is the time lapse of the piece
running, this is showing it more quickly but
you can see this idea of
abstract visuals projected on the side
of the building
this is all generative, procedural this is
a piece of software that generates this
content
that's projected on the side of a building,
this is something that's done a lot with
processing, erm, I, a
I teach a class here at ITP where the
students create work for a large video
wall
erm, here are a couple of examples of projects.
there, this is a project called Beluga
I'm skipping the sound but this was a
dance performance and
you can see that there are these dancers
that are moving and jumping on tramp-
trampolines. this a hundred twenty foot
wide video wall, it's about
twelve feet high and the visuals,
regenerative. this
seascape and they responded to the
movement's of these dancers who were
bouncing up and down
on trampolines. so this was actually, er, it's
using processing but there are three
separate computers running three
processing sketches
each controlling a section of the video
wall so even these types of
large-scale 3d
performance graphics for performance are
made with processing; another example
of this for the same space; this is a
project called replica
which err, err; here
there was a dancer live in the space
with the camera pointed at her
and her image was then a projected onto
the wall
and manipulated with a bit- series of
different kinds
of time-based effects and there's music,
the dancer
erm, and all happening in real time; all
happening
err, live.
okay I'm realizing I'm forgetting to mention
people's names but
I will- erm, there'll be links below where you can
find out the- the wonderful people who
made some of these projects so
another thing that processing is used a lot
for is for
motion graphics. this is a great project
by Molly Schwartz where she did an animation
about eels; now err, called err, Bellyful of Eels;
if you look at this a lot of this
is done with the Afterefffects,
err, but here in in in this particular part of
the
the err, animation, these eels that are
actually swimming through this
underwater pipe sewer like space; those
were actually made in processing;
rendered out from processing;
and incorporated into a larger animation
project and
there are lots of wonderful examples
music videos that have been made with
processing
err or different types of elements that
you wouldn't want to
hand animate, that need an algorithmic, generative process to,
whether it's behaviors or repetition err,
were done with code with processing
okay another, err, another co-
like popular use of processing is for
data visualization
a I'll show you a well-known project by
Jere Thorpe
This here is a visualization it's
grabbing
data from Twitter and looking for people
who said, you know
who are very excited about the fact that-
just landed in Hawaii, for example
so anyone who posted 'just landed Hawaii'
if it was me- I wish I would have gone to Hawaii,
I've never been there-
but erm, my home location on Twitter will
be New York
Jere- the project parses out
the locations New York and Hawaii and the time
that the tweet was posted
and draws a, this kinda arc path from
the original location to the landing location so
its a visualization of people posting on
twitter
about their flight and you can see
different views there's this kind of
like horizontal view now
it's spinning around, all this is done through
code
through an algorithmic process to
visualize this data and you can see
kinda
ah, erm, well you can't really see that but
ah,
up here  at the top left um this timescale
showing where we are and
this er, ah where we are in time. so this is a
a great use of processing and it looks like oh
my goodness this very like complicated
crazy 3d- how I could ever possibly
learn how to do this;
we're going to start with some very basic
things like how to draw a circle how to
move a circle
this is really just doing that also is
just lots of circles,
a little bit of 3d, the- what's happening with
those circles is controlled by data
so all this stuff is possible through
learning the
foundations of programming and a a
little bit about how to draw- do stuff
with computer graphics as well.
ah, so I'll I'll- this is a great
project by Mary Wong
if you're interested a lot of
wonderful work is being done with
processing to create physical so if you
want to print design
I would a checking out the work of Rune Matthiesen
and err,
course he teaches call Printing Code,
there's a tremendous suite of examples of
using computation
to generate print designs, err, this is a
project that Mary
Huang made to create a, err, fashion designed
through, through a generative process so you
can see here, the mouse- this is a processing
sketch running-
with the mouse able to draw over the
figure of a, the human form
and that and that what the mouse is
drawing is that
a mated to geometry, which is used to
generate the,
the design for a dress and Mary actually
created these dresses and
physically fabricated them and wore them
as well and so
a lot of stuff can be is being done
processing in terms of, erm
take a look at the work at nervous
system, I'll include a link to that as
well
for making jewelry designs you can print
stuff- you can generate stuff for a
maker bot with processing to do 3d
printing
this is something that you could
explore a as an application that you
might-
an idea you might do throughout if
you're following along with all these
videos
erm, also doing- a creating a
erm, a physical computing interfaces; this
is a project
called the mud tub um which
kinda answers that question what's the
thing that you might want to get
least near your computer- a big pile mud,
this is by Tom Gerhard,
on and so this is also kind of interesting to
say like
what you're
learning here might not might not need
to make something that has this really
obvious practical like-
I wanna make an app, and I wanna like sell
billions of them become a
zillionaire which actually is
would be nice, but you know anyway
there's more to life than
selling your apps, but err, this you can
see here
there's a projection on this tub of mud
which is- the graphics that's being
output
is done through processing and
processing is reading
the sensors that are coming back in um
from the mud
err, there's actually sensors underneath
the mud that's measuring the weight of the
mud at any
point which allows the the software to
read the topology essentially of the mud
and you can see the mud becomes this
controller where
you with your hands you can kind bounce
this ball around if I
kinda skip to the end here you can see you
can kinda play this
game here on a separate screen by
pressing on the mud
so this idea of making your own physical
computing device
your own interface a tub of mud;
another great example of this
is err the scrollable project; I'll just
show you err
this is by Filippo Vanucci and you can
see here is his processing
ah, shoot!
which I think err, here is his processing
sketch which
a if you look at it, makes this nice ink
effect
so he's created this a sketch
and if I click around here you can see
it draws a bunch of dots and it makes this
animation that has this ink like quality to it
so what did he use this process sketch
for? he used it to project onto paper
and he built sensors to measure how
what that paper's doing. this will become
much more obvious when I show you it in a
project called scrollables.
and you can see these are these devices
that you can scroll the paper and I'll
just skip ahead here
by scrolling back and forth you can
control and animation so of course we're
all familiar with touchscreens
a but here we had this physical device
which has real tactile tangible quality. because
real paper that you're scrolling and you
can see as you scroll back and forth
you can play for example the game pong
and this ink effect was created through
an algorithm in processing and/or a
and control through the physical
interface so
you know this is very very, err, a really
really quick and dirty kind of- I don't
know if I missed anything
key that I wanted to show you really kinda
quick and dirty, just quick range of
projects that
were made in processing. I would also
encourage you to
on the processing website um at
to go take a look at the exhibition so
if you look at the exhibition link
there is a ton of projects that you
can see historically you can actually go
it's
and you can actually go all the way back
if on the bottom here
oh boy,
this is getting awkward- at the bottom
here if you click on
number one you can actually see stuff
that was posted for the process exhibition
from
over 10 years ago
so this is there's a if you want to kind
of get a sense that the landscape of
what this processing do what are the
kinds of things that I'm going to learn
you could walk yourself through the examples
you can look at a bunch of projects that
are made with processing but
ultimately the rest of these videos are going
to very
slowly by slowly piece by piece walk you
through the fundamentals of programming
through a whole lot of graphic examples
and processing and that will help you
generate ideas
and things that you want that you might
wanna make and that
really well hopefully one more
introductory video to make
and that is a video where I'm just going to
talk through kind of the table of contents
everything we're gonna go through you
could call it a syllabus if you want to
but I'm kind
of afraid to do that. so I'm gonna kind of just
give you a quick overview I think this
I'm kinda having a problem with this is
that in the last one to a bit too long
so
and give you a quick overview all the
fundamentals are going to learn
and then we're just gonna dive right in and
get started