Hi! So this video I'm making is about
a function in p5js called map().
So there is a very common scenario
that comes up over and over again
in programming graphics,
programming interaction,
working with data,
there is so many places where
this scenario comes up
and so this particular function map()
is a nice resolution to this problem.
Let me give you a simple version
of this problem:
so let's say we have a canvas,
and the canvas has a background color
and what you want is
for this background color
to sometimes be black
and sometimes be white.
So when it's black
the color you should put
in the background function
is 0.
When it is white, the color
you should put in the background function
is 255.
So we can say, together,
the range for the background function
that I want in this particular program
is a number between 0 and 255.
So really a variable might go here
like, uh, we'll call it 'col'
and 'col' should have a range
between 0 and 255.
Now, how do I want that
value to be chosen?
When should it be black
and when should it be white?
What I would like is:
when the mouse pointer is
at this side of the screen
I want the background to be black,
and when the mouse pointer is
at this side of the screen
I want the background to be white.
So I would like to create a scenario
where I move the mouse
left and right, left and right,
and I see the background
shift from black all the way to white,
down to grey, darker grey,
down to black etc etc.
So this is what we want to program.
Now let's say this canvas has
dimensions of 600x400.
So mouseX is a variable, if you've
been watching these videos in sequence
[ramble]
so if these are the dimensions
of the canvas
we know that mouseX has a range
that goes between 0 and 600.
[ramble]
And the background color we want
to have a range between 0 and 255.
So we need to take this value, with
this range, and what we wanna do
is map it to this range.
When mouseX=0,
background color = 0.
When mouseX = 600,
background color = 255.
That's kinda like, let's start doing
that a little bit for a moment
without the map function at all.
Ok, so here's the program ... I'm actually
gonna simplify this for a second.
var col = 0;
I'm gonna say: background color
contains 'col',
and you can see this!
So we can see here I am running
this program, this ellipse
is being drawn where the mouse is,
so we can see, and the background
is being color according to that variable (col).
The background color is not changing
because I set it equal to 0,
and I never changed it.
So now I could try to do some math,
like I could just say:
col = mouseX;
why not? that's pretty good.
Whatever the value of mouseX is
set the background color to that!
So let's see what happens.
I'm gonna run this.
Look it's working ...
it's changing but it's already white!
Why? Because as soon as I get
to the pixel 255
that's the full whiteness!
So I am not getting this perfect mapping,
it's kinda like working but it's
not exactly right.
So I could be approximate,
I can say: ok, let's,
the canvas is 600 pixels wide,
why don't I divide by 2?
That's pretty good ...
600, or whatever the mouseX is,
divide it by 2, that's
getting me pretty close
It actually kinda looks like it's working
and we kind of solved the problem
but here's the thing:
this problem that we have just
barely solved over there
this is a very simplistic view of it.
But there's a lot of times where you
have a sensor, like data coming in
from some sensor and the range is between,
you know, 321 and 1057,
and then you wanna map that range
to some other set of values
and actually that other set of values
has a range between 20 and 35
and the math is a little bit trickier.
Or perhaps you want to take a value
that goes between 0 and 200
and invert that and map that between
200 down to 0.
So there's a lot of more complex scenarios.
The map function is a general function
that will take any range and map
a value inside that range to
a new value in any other range.
So, let's take a look ...
... how that works in this context.
So, first of all, what do I mean by function?
So already you know, hopefully,
about calling functions in p5, right?
You might have done this:
line() is a function that takes 4 arguments.
1, 2, 3, 4 ... and what does it do?
It draws a line from a point 100,100
to a point 50,50. Done.
So map() is the same thing:
it's a function that takes
some amount of arguments.
It's actually gonna be 5 arguments.
[ramble]
map() it takes 5 arguments: 1,2,3,4,5.
Can you see all those? Yes.
Ok, this seems like: oh, boy,
5 arguments! that's terrifying!
But actually it's not so bad.
So, remember: I have a range
that goes between 0 and 600,
this is the range we know that
mouseX is, and I wanna map
this range to a range between 0 and 255,
which is what I want to assign
to my variable 'col'.
So the arguments that map() requires
are the following:
what is the minimum and maximum
of my current range? 0 to 600.
What is the minimum and maximum
of my new range? 0 to 255.
And what is the value that has this range,
which I want to map to the new range?
Well, in this case it's mouseX.
So I want to map mouseX, which I know
has this range, that's the x values,
and I want to map it to
this range between 0 and 255
for the purpose of color.
And then when I map it,
what do I do with it?
I want to take the result of that mapping
and assign the result to my variable 'col'.
So this is what's actually something
quite new about this map() function.
The line() function performs a task:
line! it draws a line in the canvas.
The map() function actually performs
a calculation and answers a question,
it resolves to a single number,
so I can use that number
and assign it back to this variable, ok?
So this is kind of a new concept.
Let's go try to do it in this program.
So instead of my goofy-like math here,
mouseX/2,
what I wanna do now
is use that map() function.
So I'm gonna go over here
and I'm gonna say:
map(mouseX, 0, 600, ...
(oops, I'm gonna zoom back out)
and give me a new value within
a new range between 0 and 255.
So here: mouseX between 0 and 600
give me a range between 0 and 255,
and assign that to this variable 'col',
which I'm then gonna use in background().
and watch this ...
we can see all the way,
perfectly white at pixel 600,
perfectly black at pixel 0.
Let's have a little more fun with this!
Uh, fun is all relative, of course.
Let's give ourselves two more variables,
so I'm gonna make a variable 'r' and 'b',
r for red, b for blue,
and what I'm going to do is
I'm going to set the red value
equal to that mapping,
so you can see now ...
blue is at 255, red is at 0,
and r is getting that mapping with mouseX,
so as I move to the right
I get more pink and purple,
all the way back more blue,
and here's something interesting
that I could do with map()
let's also map the blue value
but instead of saying: when the mouse is at 0,
the blue is at 0,
when the mouse is at 600,
the blue is at 255, let's do the reverse!
Let's say that when the mouse it at 0
we have 255 blue,
and when the mouse it all the way
the other side we have 0 blue.
So we can also invert that range,
which is great that map will do that for us.
And ... all the way we can see
I get all the way red,
all the way blue, and in the middle
I've got red and blue together.
So, and also by the way,
you might take this exercise
maybe add mouseY to it,
try to map mouseY,
there's all sorts of possible things
you can do with this.
So hopefully that gives you a bit
of a sense of the map() function
and that you found that useful, possibly.
Ok, I'm gonna stop this.