Ok, so I am back here an
I'm talking about variables,
I hope ... if I can keep my brain
working and churning
and making sense with the language
and speaking thing, this will work.
So what did we look at in
the previous video?
We made this kind of big leap
in our programming lives!
Right? We established the fact
that there is a flow to a program.
What is that flow?
At least in p5js, the environment
that I'm looking at in these videos,
the flow is defined by two functions:
the setup function, which happens once,
and only once, and the draw function,
which loops over and over again.
Typically a thing that you might do
in setup() is to create your canvas.
That happens just once,
when the program starts.
Typically what you might do in draw(),
which loops over and over again,
is draw stuff.
And we established the fact that if
instead of using a number,
a hardcoded number,
we put in a variable, a word that
stands in for a number,
then each time draw() executes
if that number changes
something different might happen and
that's how animation happens on the screen.
The ellipse is drawn where the mouse is,
then the mouse moves, and it's drawn
where the mouse is, then the mouse moves etc.
So this was an exciting first step into
the world of variables.
But here's the thing:
there's gonna be a lot more
you wanna do besides just
move things with the mouse.
And even if there are other built-in
variables, like you can know
how many times has draw executed,
there's a built-in variable called frameCount,
but ultimately what you will need
is your own variables.
Variables that you make up,
that you define, that you bring into this world!
You're going to bring variables
into this world and that's gonna
open up a lot of possibilities
that you didn't have before.
So, for example,
this circle is moving across the screen
according to the mouse,
what if you want that circle,
I'm not even touching the mouse!,
I just opened my program and
that circle just moves on its own. Magic!
So this is our first step!
That's what we wanna do.
Instead of using a built-in variable
we want to use our own variables.
So how do we do that?
So we need a couple steps:
step 1 is to declare the variable.
[ramble]
number 2 is we need to initialize.
We need to say: aha, in addition to
the fact that I declare this variable
I will give it an initial value
and then the 3rd step is,
optionally, use the variable.
Although it wouldn't make a lot of sense
to declare and initialize a variable
if you didn't intent to use it.
So how do we do this?
Declare is actually something
quite simple:
all you have to do is to write
the term 'var', which stands for 'variable'.
This is how you do it in Javascript,
in order languages it's different.
var ... so this means I am now about
to declare a variable!
The next thing I have to do
is give that variable a name.
And that name can be absolutely
anything I choose.
'rainbow' is a nice name,
for a variable.
But ultimately what you want to do
is probably name it with
something that is a term that's
associated with what you might
intend the variable to do.
So what I intend to do with this variable
that I am declaring
is use it as the x-position of this circle.
So I might say:
circleX, is the name of my variable.
I'm just gonna use the word 'circleX'
typically I'm just kind of being
longwinded but you could
even just name it 'x'.
There's a bunch of rules like
you can't start a variable's name
with a number, you can't use
strange characters in the variable,
but you'll figure that out
through trial and error.
Mostly you just wanna use words
and you cannot have any spaces.
So declare and name.
To declare is saying 'var' and the name.
So now I could say:
circleX instead of mouseX
So actually that's 'use',
so I've done step 1 and
I've done step 3,
use the variable, but if you think about it,
(I need a semicolon here)
if you think about it
there's a huge missing piece here, right?
Because what's the value of circleX?
I mean it could be anything.
Right now it's actually technically,
in Javascript, the value is undefined.
I think I'm right about that ...
someone will correct me if I'm wrong.
But it's undefined because I never
gave it an initial value.
This is important.
It's not gonna be able to draw at circleX
anywhere unless we give it an
initial value.
And so I could write here in setup() ...
I could say 'circleX = 50;'
So this is giving it, initializing it ...
and look at this statement:
this is called, this is something
totally new,
the only thing if you've only been
watching these videos and this is
all you know about programming
all we had were function calls,
createCanvas(), background(), ...
now we have something new.
This is what's known as an
assignment operation.
We are assigning the value 50
to the variable circleX,
we would not have been able to do this
if we hadn't declared our intention
to use circleX, and notice
the declaration is at the top of our code,
and our initialization is in setup().
The truth of the matter is
even though I showed you
these as two separate steps,
I'm kind of showing this because
it's kind of interesting like:
look, that's something else that you
might do in setup()
at the beginning of my program
I want this variable value to equal
to some initial value.
But the truth of the matter is
most of the time, and in all the examples
that you're gonna see,
step 1 and 2 will be combined.
And so I'm now gonna rewrite this
[?]
So I can both declare and initialize
the variable instantly by saying:
var circleX = 50;
ok?
So we've done something ...
we've declared a variable
saying 'var', giving it a name and
an initial value and we're using it
to stand in for something in our code.
Let's go take a look at this
actually work over here.
Ok, so here's a little program ...
if I run it you can see
what exactly we have.
We have an ellipse being drawn
only ever at location 50.
So it doesn't move.
So now let's add that stuff to our program.
So at the top
I'm gonna say: var circleX,
and by the way,
you can declare, we're gonna see
later that you can declare
variables in other places,
but for right now,
as a constraint, I would like to say:
all the variables get declared at the top.
Let's just use that as
a constraint right now.
Then I'm gonna give it
an initial value, equal to 50.
And right here, instead of
saying ellipse(50
I'm gonna say ellipse(circleX
and I'm gonna run it.
Look at that!
Same exact program,
only instead of hardcoding 50 there,
50 is up here.
Ok, now ...
let's just prove that this is
actually working
I'm gonna say '150'
and stop and start it.
Look! That circle is a little
bit further.
Now I'm gonna say '250'
and look, the circle is even
a little bit further over.
So whatever the value of circleX is
that's where that ellipse will be drawn.
Ok, at the beginning of this video,
in my mind was: I would like
to make that circle move
by itself across the screen.
You're watching all these videos
and all you get is a little circle
that moves across the screen
but it'll lead, hopefully,
to bigger and better things!
How are we gonna do that?
So let's come back over here for a second.
What I want to do ...
is the following:
I want the circle
first to be drawn at
circleX =50
So, remember:
draw(), which is this function,
is looping over and over again,
it's over and over again,
it happens once, it happens another time,
another time,
so first I want to draw it at 50
then maybe I want it to draw at 51
the next time maybe I want
to draw it at 52,
the next time maybe 53, right?
Each time draw() loops, executes again,
I want the circle to be drawn
one pixel over from the previous time.
So if you had to write an instruction
to do that, each time to draw,
what would you say?
You might say 'increment circleX
by 1', you know?
Take 1, add 1 to circleX
You might say 'add 5 to circleX',
and it'll move from 0 to 5,
to 10, to 15, to 20, ... right?
So how do we write that with code?
Here is a way ... remember we had
an assignment operation
circleX = 50
there's something weird you can do ...
it's a common thing in programming
but at first it might seem a little weird.
circleX = circleX + 1;
Now look at that statement.
For a moment you might look
at that and think:
that's like a paradox ...
that's impossible ...
a number cannot equal itself plus 1!
5 does not equal to 6,
7 does not equal to 8,
20 does not equal to 21 ...
but this is not what we're doing.
I am not testing for equality here.
This is an assignment operation!
What I am saying is:
take circleX and set it equal to
the value of itself plus 1.
So if circleX is equal to 50,
50 + 1 = 51,
and now assign that value to circleX.
circleX is now 51.
Now run through draw() again,
take the value of circleX, 51,
add 1 to it, 52,
assign that value back to circleX.
So in an assignment operation
the right-hand side of the equation
is always evaluated and then
assigned to the left-hand side.
This is an incrementation operation.
We're just taking a variable
and adding 1 to it, over and over again
because draw() loops.
So let's go over here and see ...
First, let's start circleX at 0.
So I just change circleX to starting at 0.
And you can see there it is at 0
and now I'm going to add
that line of code:
circleX = circleX +1;
Every time through draw()
circleX will go up by 1.
Yay! It's moving! Tadaaa!
Ok, so that really worked.
So I know this is like incredible
simplistic and basic in terms of the result
but this is the foundation
upon which you can build
a lot of interesting things.
Because there is a lot more math,
there's a lot more ways
you can change a variable,
besides just adding 1 to it.
There's a lot more places
you could put variables
besides just in the x-spot.
So what I would say to you
right now is:
why don't you try to make
a variable for the y-position?
Why don't you try to make a variable
for the size of the circle?
Can you make the circle grow?
Can you make it shrink?
Can you make a color change?
See if you can make up more
variables, declare more variables
at the top, and put them
in different places
and try to do stuff to them.
The truth of the matter is
in order to get
more interesting results
you're going to need something
that I'm going to talk about
in a future video:
conditional logic,
because, you know, here's
the next logical thing:
first, let's make it go
a little bit faster,
like circleX = circleX + 10;
Like, oh, that circle, no, no,
don't go away!
Come back! Come back!
It's never gonna come back!
But if I made some conditional logic
like: if it gets to the end
then turn around and come back,
you know, that's something
I'm gonna do in a future video
but for now, just try to
add a bunch of variables
and see what you can get.
Ok, that's good.
There's gonna be another video
in a moment where I am
going to show you a different
way of organizing your variables.
I'm a little skeptical about
whether that's a good idea or not
but I'm gonna do it!