So, hopefully by now you've
played a little bit with variables in p5.
Maybe you used mouseX, mouseY,
you made up some of your own variables.
And I want to look actually
at an example,
it doesn't really have
a lot more to it,
this example is just like the one
I made previously,
where I have a circle that's just
moving across the screen.
And you can see here:
how did I do that?
There's an incrementation
operation right down here:
that every time through draw()
x goes up by 1.
So first the circle's here,
then it goes up by one,
then it's here, then it's here,
etc
So that how you move something
on the screen.
Now one thing I did here
is I added a whole lot
of other variables.
Let's have a 'y' and a 'diameter'
for the size of that circle.
And R, G, B variables for the background.
So maybe I could do some
things like increment
the red amount, decrement
the green amount.
And hopefully these are the kinds
of things that you've been playing with.
And what I wanna do
in this video
is show you a way
to organize your variables.
And while it seems a little bit
silly and premature perhaps,
this is fine!, I'm not actually
gonna change anything
about this program,
but I'm just going to change
the way it's organized.
And this is going to set
a foundation for later,
as well as help you to just
keep your code in a neat and tidy way,
which is something that I'm
a little too obsessed about
and I'm really working on it,
I really am, I swear.
Ok, so let's think about how
that could work.
So let's just say for the moment
that I have a variable x,
and it has an initial value of 0.
And I have a variable y and
it has an initial value of 100.
And I have a variable diameter
which has an initial value of 50.
So these three variables they go together, right?
I'm using them for that circle:
x for the x-position of that circle
on the screen,
y for the y-position of that circle
and the diameter for that circle
on the screen.
And while this relationship
of these variables is only
something in my mind,
Javascript doesn't care!
The computer doesn't care. You can
use these variables for anything.
I could plug that x value into
the color for something,
and it would work.
It might be helpful if I could
put all of these together.
And there is a way I could do that.
I can say: 'var' and I can say 'circle'
So I have the circle on the screen
and I'm gonna call it a 'circle'.
And then what I am going to do is:
equals, and I'm going to have
an open curly bracket
and a close curly bracket.
So circle is now,
what is happening is,
you could think of 'circle' as
a container.
What I would like to do is
instead of having 3 variables
floating on their own,
I would like to not have
these 3 variables floating on their own,
but I would like to put those 3 variables
inside of this variable called 'circle'.
In order to do that I'm gonna say:
x: 0,
(boy, I really hope I'm getting
the syntax of this right, cause
this is new for me!)
And if I get it wrong, I could always
make it again. I'm sure somebody
on the Internet will tell me,
if anybody actually watches this.
y: 100, diameter: 50
Now where the line breaks are
doesn't actually matter.
The curly brackets matter.
The colons matter, the commas matter.
So you can see that, just like setup(),
function setup() was a block of code,
with a beginning and an end,
function draw() is
a block of code with
a beginning and an end,
this variable 'circle' now has a block
of code with a beginning and an end,
and 'circle' is a container for
these three variables.
Now container is actually not
the technical term for this,
and what is interesting about
what you have just seen here,
you have now learned about
Javascript objects.
The syntax for this is
Javascript object notation.
The way that you create an object,
this 'circle' is an object,
and that object has data inside of it:
it has an x, a y and a diameter.
And boy, are we gonna someday
get to some really exciting stuff
where we see that an object
can also have behaviors
and so much more to it.
But right now, you can think
of 'there is my circle object
and I'm visualising my circle object
on the screen,
I'm visualising its data.
Its x is 0, its y is 100
and its diameter is 50.
By the way, I'm using these terms
by accident, what is super exciting
about this is, look at this,
we're not gonna get to this
for many, many videos,
this is exactly how you get data
from lots of things.
So if you wanna get today's weather
in to your p5js sketch
you might connect to some
weather service that's gonna
send you data.
It's gonna send you data
exactly like this.
weather = {
temperature: , high temperature:
so learning this syntax is going
to lay the foundation
for just about everything
you do in Javascript.
Here is a Javascript object.
So let's now look at how
we implement this in the code.
So I'm coming back over here,
and instead of these 3 variables,
and we're gonna find out
if I did this correctly syntax-wise
x:0, y:200,
oops, I put a semicolon there,
a comma is actually correct,
and then diameter:50
and I can put a semicolon there.
So this is really one line of code.
It ends with a semicolon,
but I'm breaking it into separate lines,
and I may use p5editor's
auto-format,
whoops,
which you can see, sort of
auto-formatted it for me
and this is sort of a
standard way of doing it.
So, that was a bit of a digression.
But I just noticed a little bug
in the editor which I'm gonna file.
So x is 0, y is 200 and diameter is 50.
So I can remove these variables
from the top
and I'm gonna hit 'save'
and now I'm gonna run this.
Aha! Now look at this.
This is also a key moment
because, boy, are you gonna
have a lot of errors happening
when you run your code.
So I'm gonna zoom in
to the bottom here,
and we can see: what is this error?
'Uncaught ReferenceError: x is not defined'
on line 20.
So I'm gonna zoom back out
and go down to line 20,
ah, x is not defined.
well, x is no longer defined,
I didn't declare a variable named 'x'.
What I did is I declared a variable
named 'circle', which is an object,
and one of the fields,
the pieces of data of that object is 'x'.
So how do I get then that x
which is inside of the circle?
And the way that you do that
is with something known as
'dot syntax', right?
When I just had this variable,
variable x, I just said:
ellipse(x,
So now what do I want to do?
I wanna draw the ellipse at what?
I wanna draw the ellipse at
the circle's x, right?
The x inside circle.
And the way that I get there
is I refer to the variable name
'circle' and I get to that
x value inside with a dot.
dot x.
circle.x
Okay, let's go back now, over here.
And come down to here,
and I'm gonna say:
circle.x, circle.y,
circle.diameter, circle.diameter
Ok, oh, look at this!
I already forgot, I was like
Oh, let's run this again!
and it says 'uncaught error' on line 22,
that x is not defined
because I need to change this to:
circle.x and circle.x
So I run this and we've got
the same exact program now.
Again, nothing new is happening here.
The same exact program as before
but I did do something interesting
which is I organised a bunch
of variables into something.
Which leads me to a point where
I'm like: maybe this might be
useful if I were to make two of them, right?
circle1 and circle2
This way I don't have all these
x1, x2, y1, y2 ...
everything floating around.
So this way of organising your
collections of variables
that are being used together
conceptually into an object
can really help you organize
and keep track of things
and lays a good foundations
for a lot of things.
There's a lot more we're gonna do with
object oriented programming later
and it also sets a foundation for
working with data
that comes from other sources
because it will have exactly
the same syntax.
So as an exercise that you might
try for yourself is:
see if you can take something
you're working on,
reorganize your variables into these objects,
and if you're looking at this one,
try to make two objects,
try to maybe make your own
color object that has
an R, G, B and an alpha perhaps in it,
those are things that you can try to do!
And hopefully this video
was useful and interesting to you!
And I finished recording it.
Excellent, good bye!