So here we are, this is the last video
in this little section
about variables in p5js
and before I go,
although I'm not going anywhere
because all I do is stay in this room
and make videos,
before I go on to the next topic,
which is conditional logic,
which will really unlock a lot
of creative possibilities for you,
I wanna give you one last tool
that hopefully will make things
a little bit more exciting, in your life.
And that is the random() function.
So the random() function ...
We, you and me, together,
have been doing a lot of stuff like this:
var x = 50;
and this is well and good,
because x is a variable and
50 is a perfectly fine number
and I'm happy with my rectangle
at pixel 50.
But there might be a time ... the whole point
of doing this programming thing
is to have systems of logic,
rules to generate behaviors
and graphics and designs.
It's not really about let me pick
my five favorite numbers
and set those variables to those numbers.
So there is a lot more to it,
but a first step in that direction
is that we can at least say:
here is the rule,
whenever my programs runs,
the circle will appear at a random x-location.
So instead of saying var x = 50;
I could say something like
var x = random ... and random()
is a function just like any other function,
line(), ellipse(), fill(), stroke(),
it requires some arguments
to define how that function will behave,
and random(), if you've watched
the previous video, is just like
the map() function,
and if you recall, or if you didn't watch it,
the difference is when you say
line(), a line is drawn on the screen,
the line function performs a task.
When you say random(), a task is performed
(picking a random number)
but that function resolves to,
evaluates to that number
and you can take that number
what it resolves to and assign it
back to something,
a variable value in this case.
So if I say 0 comma 50
the parameters, the arguments that
random() takes
are a minimum and a maximum.
And random() will give you a number
inbetween 0 and 50.
One thing that's important here to realize,
which is a small, little distinction,
is that, here's some numbers that you
might get: 2, 21, 73 .. uh, no, not 73,
that's above 50!
42, but I will mention you probably
won't ever get these ... you COULD
get these but more likely you'll get numbers
like this ... it's giving you, what is
sometimes referred to as
floating point numbers or decimal numbers.
So in this case it doesn't really matter,
p5 can handle that.
If you get the number 50.34567 it knows
to just draw something at pixel 50.
But there is other cases where
we might need to do a little something
more with that.
I should probably not have mentioned this ...
cause it's a little unnecessary
point of confusion but I've already
started , restarted this video like 5 times!
So I am going for it.
Ok, so let's actually start messing
around with this and see what happens.
Ok, so I have a sketch here ...
Actually, I'm gonna start a new one ...
...
and what I would like to do
is have some variables,
and I'm gonna use objects, since we
learned about, I've covered them
in a previous video.
So I have a point
and I'm also gonna have a color
Let's see how I'm doing here
with just having learned Javascript syntax!
So you can see I'm setting up
a couple variables
I wanna have a 'point' that has
an x and a y,
I wanna have a 'col' that has
a 'r', a 'g', and a 'b' because
my plan for all this is, first in setup,
obviously to create a canvas,
let's make it a nice small size,
and then what I'm gonna do
is I'm gonna set a background
in setup() cause background()
should just happen once.
And then an ellipse ... I'm gonna
draw the ellipse at point.x, point.y
it's gonna be a small ellipse,
and I'm gonna fill it with col.r, col.g and col.b
So I can zoom back out here
and we can see we should be able to run
this sketch now, hit run ...
Uh, ok, 'problem with scope' ...
What happened?
Look at this, interesting.
ellipse is receiving an empty variable
in spot number 1, 2 ... this is not intentional ...
[trying to figure out the problem]
I put some semicolons here ...
What did I miss?
Help!
Look at this ...
What am I doing here?
Oh, ellipse ... no, oh, look!
Some crazy stuff has happened here ...
Some horrible stuff ...
this video is a disaster!
I'm gonna fix it ...
I cut this out if I remember to ...
point, comma, ...
[trying to figure out problem]
Let's do some things ...
First, when we have these kinds of problems
this is a useful point, let's just comment out
the offending lines of code,
hit save and hit run ...
Ok, no errors anymore!
Let's comment back in fill() ...
We can figure out what's going on ...
Still no errors!
Let's draw an ellipse the old-fashioned way ...
and let's see if this works ...
Ok, that seems good!
Now what is wrong with
my point.x and my point.y?
Let's try this ... point.x
Let's run it again.
Ah, 'empty variable in spot 1' ...
I wonder if 'point' ...
let's call it 'spot' ...
I wonder if there's something wrong
with using 'point'
Yeah!
Ha, that was interesting ...
I've got to look into that!
So I don't know if 'point' must be
some keyword that's doing ...
Ooohhhh! I've done something horrible!
Boy, wow, this is great!
This is great! Ok!
I know what happened.
I know what happened. This is great.
Ok, so here's the thing:
What did I just do?
Let's think of some functions in p5,
I know I'm off on like this horrible
tangent for another 5 minutes ...
Some functions in p5are like line(),
rect() for drawing a rectangle,
ellipse() for drawing an ellipse,
What if you wanna draw a point
on the screen, huh?
What's the name of that function again?
point()!
So point() is kind of like an important
thing in p5 that's meant
for something highly specific:
drawing a point!
So if I try to make up a variable
called point ...
I have completely overriden
the existing point() function
and you know what?
I didn't actually override it cause
p5 then overrode my variable
cause things are happening
in a weird order and strange ways.
So that didn't work, it was trying like
use the point() function as the place
to draw the point and everything
exploded and I got a weird error message.
So that might be something that p5
could handle with a friendlier message,
and maybe after this video is over,
someone will file a github issue,
maybe that person will be me.
But let's go back, and hopefully
you saw the steps of debugging
of like everything was exploding
and going wrong ... just keep calm,
take a deep breath,
calm down, comment some stuff out,
start putting it back into slowly,
seeing where things go wrong,
we've gotten a bit further.
But now we're back! I'm back.
This video is still only at 8 minutes,
which is totally reasonable,
and we're going to go back
and change this to 'spot'
I'm gonna say: spot.x , spot.y
and I'm gonna run it ...
and we can see: there we go!
I have the circle ... and I'm gonna
move this over here ...
being drawn
Excuse me, I'm like, ...
I want this to give me a little more space.
I have the circle being drawn
at 100, 50 where the spot is
with this particular color.
So what happens if we start
to add some randomness here?
So one thing I could do ...
first, remember: draw() is looping
over and over again ...
so what if I just say:
spot.x = random(0,600); ?
This is another thing worth mentioning:
I have a random spot anywhere
between 0 and the width of that canvas,
the width of that canvas is 600
so I could write the number 600 there.
There does happen to be a built-in variable
in p5 that knows just dynamically
what the width of the window is
and this is useful to use because
if I use that variable 'width' here
instead of typing '600', if I later
change the size in createCanvas()
I don't have to change elsewhere in my code.
So I am gonna do that.
And I'm also gonna say:
spot.y = random(0, height);
So now let's run this program ...
And look! I just get spots all over the place:
spots, spots, spots.
All with a nice red color.
But perhaps what I want is
to say: col.r = random(100,255);
col.g = 0;
col.b = random(100,190);
I'm just picking random, arbitrary ranges here.
And now we might see ...
Look: I've got a nice variation
of random purple-ish, pink-ish dots
and I could even say:
add a little bit of alpha here,
and run this again ...
and you can see I have
a nice little pointillist, and you can actually,
one thing you're noticing here,
if you look really closely,
there's this little black outline
because I didn't turn of the stroke.
So what I am going to do now
is say: noStroke();
and stop and start ...
and there ... just look at this
beautiful, all these nice, little dots
layering, nice, little pointillist thing ...
So you can take this much further,
you can make random sizes,
you can map the random ranges
based on like where ...
like: if the dots appear on the left
they're more greenish, if they're
on the right, they're more blue-ish,
so there is so much you could do!
Maybe try to create a random
painting here, you could use other shapes
besides just circles, that sort of thing
as an exercise you could try,
You also might return to this particular
program if you remember this,
we worked just on a little bit
of a painting program
where you move the mouse around
and as you move the mouse around
you paint something,
and so what if you could, every time
you click the mouse it erases the background,
what if every time you click the mouse
you get a random background color?
Or as you move the mouse
the colors changes randomly?
So there's a lot of
interesting possibilties there,
you can make this painting program
a little more sophisticated.
Ok, so that is the end of this video!
And I think this wraps up my section
of videos on variables
and I'm gonna keep that weird
little thing that happened,
that I think was a good moment
for today.
Ok, see you later!