Okay, look, let's take a step back for a second
and let me introduce myself a little more properly.
My name is (this is absurd but I'm writing my name over here
on the board but) my name is [enunciating] Daniel Sheef Mon
pronounced 'Shiffman'
but I don't know, you can say Sheef Mon if you want
and I work at a place called ITP which you can find out more about at
ITP.nyu.edu
It's a two-year graduate program and I
teach a lot of programming courses here, one of which
in particular is a course called 'Introduction
to Computational Media' in which the students
learn - most them for the very first time - how to program the computer
and we use for that course something else that I participate
in developing, called, 'Processing,' and you can find out more about Processing
at Processing.org so this is who I am the kind of context, at least, of what I'm doing
I imagine I'm making these videos just to try them, to learn more about teaching -
to learn more about teaching in this strange
new context as well as to supplement the course that I'm teaching here
but it is my hope that all the things will kind of feed into each other in a nice
way and that there will be some population, however small, whether it's
three people - three hundred - three thousand - three billion - that are
interested in this content and that this stuff that I'm going to talk about
and demonstrate over many many, many, many, many videos
on will be interesting to help you with - [humorously] I don't know -
I'm really trying too hard to justify this, but I'm just doing it, you can turn it off at
anytime you like. Okay now, who are you?
I don't know. I would be interested in hearing from you.
But let me say a few things: this video series
is for the complete and total beginner.
You don't need to know anything.
That's not entirely true. You do need to access to a computer -
you probably already do if you're watching this video - you need to know
some basic stuff:
how to download a piece of software, how to install it,
yeah, how to type - that kind of stuff but really that's it.
I will assume no knowledge whatsoever about anything that has to do with
programming.
we're going to really, really slowly in great detail
build-up stuff from the beginning.
So if you already know some stuff about programming, the nice thing about these
video series is I'm trying to keep the videos
to between 2 and 20 minutes.
really I want them to be like 5 or 10 minute videos but you can just skip some
You can jump ahead. If all you're interested in how to, like, parse
a JSON feed and get it into your Processing sketch, that's probably going to be video,
like, number 50 or 30
or 22 - somewhere further ahead
(it's not made yet, by the way. It doesn't exist) but you can jump ahead and do that.
The other thing I should mention it I made some videos last year
so as you're watching them if you suddenly think that I look much younger
or have a strangely different length of beard,
it's because some of the videos from last year are going to be kind of spliced
in here although I may end up
remaking them if they're out-of-date
or needing some
extra touch-up - or that sort of thing.
So that's who I am. That's who you are -
- or maybe you are, and you can let me know if
you are somebody different.