Hello!
Aaaawk, so awkward
because it's very hard to begin these things but we're just gonna go right in
and we're going to begin
Hello my name is Dan. Perhaps you watched a video that I’ve been in before or perhaps you haven’t
I don't know how you got here but you're here, I'm here, you're here,
we're here together, there's a wall here, I can write on it
there’s gonna be a computer over there. why are we here?
Have you ever wanted to learn programming? have you never even tried to learn programming?
have you never written a line of code
before in your life? you have no idea what it means
to program to write code to create your own software?
do you want to break free from the bonds
of the tools that other people have made for you?
do you want to write your own, to build your own software?
make your own things from scratch
on the computer? If so …
this sounds like a sales pitch but really there's nothing to sell here, you could just leave
at any moment
but if so you're in the right place! this is a video series
that is going to teach you how to program
your computer. now how, what kind of, what programming language you use,
what environment you use,
what it is you want to make, is a huge giant
mess of stuff. we're gonna do things in a simple way,
I’m gonna talk a lot more about this something called Processing, I'm just going to talk
to you
going to draw diagrams, I will demonstrate for you
code examples on this computer over here
it's all going to be in video. now
you might have some questions like: oh, I get it, I heard about these things
kinda like a MOOC, I don't know how to pronounce it, is this a MOOC?
it's not a MOOC, could be a MOOC, you could make it a MOOC
but MOOCs are a little bit scary. this is just some videos
to help you learn. I hope you might find, you might do this on your own
you might use these in the conference, to supplement a class you're taking
you might be a teacher of some other people and want to use these videos in
your course
I don't know but I would like them to be helpful however you think
they might be helpful! so the other thing you might ask is
this seems a little weird just talking and drawing diagrams. you know I hear about all these
new fancy interactive online learning
test quizzing and I can … You know that those things are great
and I would like to ultimately incorporate
some stuff where you could easily look at the code while I'm
demonstrating it, trying things out. the Khan Academy is doing some fantastic stuff
John Resig and
the CS courses, I highly recommend them, they’re doing a lot of similar stuff
I'm just kinda doing what I know which is drawing to a whiteboard
and using this computing machine
to type out examples. they will all be available for you to download
there's even a book that I will hesitate to show you that you could use to follow
along
I'm also going to do some live
online live events where I am
gonna take calls and answers questions which is another …
I kinda digress here but that's gonna happen too so
that's really, I made some notes over here and I
this is a so far I’ve only been talking for three minutes, this is my intro video
but so if you really just want to get into the meat of the stuff you can skip ahead
cause I haven't made it yet
I don't know, I will link to it, I don't know the video number yet
but there's a video you can just jump to which is hey
let's start, let’s write our first line of code, let's see how everything works
but I'm going to have a few more videos just kinda talk
a little more about who I am, what I imagine you might use this for,
what is programming in perhaps a kind of general question, what our programming
languages is, what you might use that I'm using, why am I using this one versus that one
wooo … everything's gonna be okay, I think so
so I'm just gonna have a few more introductory videos, I’ll show you I hopefully
make one where I’ll
show you a bunch of your project that are kinda that you might think of as
possible outcomes or that relate to the kinds of things were going to be doing
in this
a video series so there's a bunch more intro videos that i'm gonna make, they’ll be
short five-minute videos that you can watch, but at any point
you could just stopped completely and go out, you know chess is a fun game
uhm, I don't know
put a basketball is nice, music, learning to play the violin
I did that for a while, it was very enjoyable because it's something else
or if or you can jump ahead, argh, this turned off
I have a
camera turning off problem, or you could jump ahead and kinda get to the point
where you think you’re ready to go to
okay hopefully it's going to be fine that’s the end of this video