hello
aaaawk, so awkward
because it's very hard to begin these
things but we're just gonna go right in
and we're going to begin
hello my name is Dan. Perhaps you watched a
video that I’ve been in before or perhaps you haven’t
I don't know how you got here but you're
here I'm here you're here
we're here together there's a wall here, I can write on it
there’s gonna be a computer over there. Why are we here
have you ever wanted to learn
programming
have you never even tried to learn
programming? have you never written a line of code
before in your life? you have no idea what it
means
to program to write code to create your
own software?
do you want to break free from the bonds
of the tools that other people have made for
you?
do you want to write your own, to build your own
software? make your own things from
scratch
on the computer? If so …
this sounds like a sales pitch but really there's
nothing to sell here, you could just leave
at any moment
but if so you're in the right place! this
is a video series
that is going to teach you how to
program
your computer. now how, what kind of,
what programming language you use, what
environment
what it is you want to make, is a huge
giant
mess of stuff. we're gonna do things
in a simple way,
I’m gonna talk a lot more about this something
called processing, I'm just going to talk
to you
going to draw diagrams, I will
demonstrate for you
code examples on this computer over here
it's all going to be in video. now
you might have some questions like: oh, I
get it, I heard about these things
kinda like a MOOC, I don't know
how to pronounce it, is this a MOOC?
it's not a MOOC, could be a MOOC, you could
make it a MOOC
but MOOCs are a little bit scary.
this is just some videos
to help you learn. I hope you might find, you
might do this on your own
you might use these in the conference, to
supplement a class you're taking
you might be a teacher of some other
people and want to use these videos in
your course
I don't know but I would like them to be
helpful however you think
they might be helpful! so the other
thing you might ask is
this seems a little weird just talking and drawing
diagrams. you know I hear about all these
new fancy interactive online learning
test quizzing and I can … You know
that those things are great
and I would like to alternately
incorporate
some stuff where you could easily look
at the code while I'm
demonstrating it, trying things out. the
Khan Academy is doing some fantastic stuff
John Resig and
the CS courses, I highly recommend
them, they’re doing a lot of similar stuff
I'm just kinda doing what I know which
is drawing to a whiteboard
and using this computing machine
to type out examples. they will all be
available for you to download
there's even a book that I will hesitate to
show you that you could use to follow
along
I'm also going to do some live
online live events where I am
gonna take calls and answers questions
which is another …
I kinda digress here but that's gonna happen
too so
that's really, I made some notes
over here and I
this is a so far I’ve only been talking for three
minutes, this is my intro video
but so if you really just want to get
into the meat of the stuff but you can
skip ahead
I don't know, I will link to it, I don't
know the video on
number x I haven’t made it but there's a
video you can just jump to which is hey
let's start, let’s writw our first line
of code, let's see how everything works
but I'm going to have a few more videos
just kinda talk
a little more about who I am, what I
imagine you might use this for,
what is programming in perhaps a kind of
general question, what our programming
languages is, what you might use that I'm
using, why am I using this one versus that
one
wooo … everything's gonna be
okay, I think so
so I'm just gonna have a few more
introductory videos, I’ll show you I hopefully
make one where I’ll
show you a bunch of your project that are kinda
that you might think of this
possible outcomes or that relate to the
kinds of things were going to be doing
in this
a video series so there's a bunch more
intro videos that i'm gonna make, they’ll be
short five-minute videos that you can watch,
but at any point
you could just stopped completely and go
out, you know chess is a fun game
uhm, I don't know
put a basketball is nice, music, learning
to play the violin
I did that for a while, it was very
enjoyable because it's something else
or if or you can jump ahead, argh, this
turned off
I have a
camera turning off problem, or you could
jump ahead and kinda get to the point
where you think you’re ready to go to
okay hopefully it's going to be fine
that’s the end of this video