We got a question, we just gotta
get this out of the way.
"What is programming?" I mean really...
that answer will come about... the real
answer to that question
reveals itself the more you do
programming.
But let's talk about it kind of in general
for a second, the thing we have to
realize is
okay... I wish I had like Google glasses on,
I could just like POP
show you what I'm looking at, but that
computer, there's a computer over there.
It's not very smart, it's incredibly
powerful, it's kind of amazing that they
exist, and that they can do all this stuff
but it doesn't know how to do anything.
At all.
Nothing! It needs human beings
to write instructions for it to do
certain things -- to crunch some numbers, to
draw certain colors to the screen --
everything has to be written as
instructions for the computer.
And this is really what it means to
program, to write those instructions,
to write an algorithm.
What is an algorithm? It's just
a sequential list of instructions that
solve a particular problem.
An algorithm for example -- I can't believe
I'm going to use this as an example but
you know "you put your right hand in,
you put your right hand out, you put your right
hand in and you shake it all about".
You know "Hokey Pokey". It feels really
ridiculous to do but that,
that's a program. Not for a computer to
follow perhaps but for a
toddler. As you may be painfully aware
these videos are not planned or
rehearsed!
That might be a good idea to start doing but
I went off on a tangent about the Hokey Pokey
I don't edit them either but this is a
moment we're editing.
So let's let's just sort of think of another
example here, OK?
So let's say that you need to...
you've met somebody who has very poor
dental hygiene(?) and they
never brush their teeth, and you need to
explain to them
how to brush your teeth. Well, how would
you do that? You might say
"you know the toothbrush, put toothpaste
on it and like brush it back and forth".
Right? That might be some instructions.
But what we have to realize with programming,
and one of the things that makes programming
hard, is this fact that the computer
doesn't have any intuition
or ability to -- you know -- to communicate
from human being to another human
being with instructions. There's body
language, there's intuition, there's
all sorts of ways that we communicate
without kinda detail and specificity.
Writing computer programs,
you need that specificity and that's
one of the things that's going to make it
hard I guess, is
understanding the syntax and the
fact that if I say...
um... "teeth your brush", you could probably
figure out -- that sounds a little weird --
that I meant to say "brush your teeth".
But a computer, you know, if you just left
out one word, one
letter, one semi-colon, one piece of
punctuation, the whole thing's just
not going to work at all and that's
going to make things kinda challenging.
The other... the so... but let's return to
this brushing your teeth. So let's let's
actually be even a little bit more
specific. We might say
you know the first step is "locate
toothbrush", right?
The next step is "locate toothpaste". I
don't know how absurd we need to get
you know... pick... you know, you know,
we could say like
"move finger one away from thumb".
You know, "Use the fingers to pick up the
toothbrush", right? We could get so crazy
specific. But you know,
we need to say like "squeeze the
toothpaste onto the toothbrush", right?
There's just a sequence of steps here.
And you know rather go through this
myself you might take this as a little
exercise to
yourself -- you know, really try to do
this, and then you know, find a
very willing and kind friend to try to
follow the instructions literally and
see like
did they perform the program correctly?
Were there are bugs in your system,
right?
You know how how does that
really work? But I want to mention a few
other things about
this. So let's say um...let's
consider the following
What if I said even before this step
"If it 9 a.m. do this."? Right, so
if it is 9 a.m.
locate your toothbrush, locate your
toothpaste, start these steps. So these are the
things that we...
that I'm just starting to point out,
the fact that programming,
it isn't just a matter of saying
"do this, do that,
do this". There are... there's logic, there's
there's there's a sort of sophisticated
logic that possible here, where
we start having conditions "if this
condition is met perform these steps".
That's one of the things that you want to
start thinking about right? "If it's the
morning brush your teeth.
If it's noon... I don't know... stop making this
video and go eat some lunch for God's sake."
I'm feeling a little like... woozy
but I think everything's gonna be fine,
don't worry.
Okay, so that's another thing. The
other thing I might mention is that
you might say "Okay, move...
you might... we might have a step
which is somewhere further along,
"Put bristles on front teeth."
The next step is "Move
bristles horizontally
and rapidly back and forth." Or something.
I'm just making up these steps.
"Move the bristles horizontally amd rapidly
back and forth".
I don't know... is this really... am I really
here talking about how to brush your teeth?
Oh my goodness. So you might do this, but
but but one thing we might say here
also is "repeat
number six
ten times." Sorry, I'm just showing you that
as you start to write out these steps,
think about "Are there conditions? Are
there things that get repeated?"
How would you really design
this algorithm that has a beginning, a
middle and an end
that someone could follow and no detail
would be lost?
This is really the beginning of writing
a computer program. And if you think
about
making the game "Pong" you're really going to
be doing the same thing,
right? You're going to be saying "Draw a
rectangle on the left side of the screen.
Draw a rectangle on the right side of
the screen. Draw a
rectangle... a circle... in the middle. Move
the circle towards the rectangle. If the
circle hits the rectangle, turn
the circle around, right?" This set
of steps -- "If the circle goes past the
rectangle, increase
the score of the other player
by one", right?
Try to write out a list of
instructions in English
for the game "Pong". Now there's a couple
things I want to mention about this
which is sort of exciting. One is
we have just described this concept
known as -- I don't think I spelled it
right -- "pseudo-codeo".
Pseudocode. This is something
that... uh... you will want to do in your
future life, unless you've already turned this off
and you're bike riding or... I don't
know, having a nice
salad with a little... some nuts and
cranberries is nice. But anyway...
but pseudocode is something
that you want to get used to doing, right?
The syntax of programing can be
challenging,
difficult and hard to do. If you can plan
out your code
in English -- or whatever your language is,
whatever your language you think and
write and speak in --
then you can begin to design the
steps of your program
in advance, which will help you when you
go to sit down to actually write the
actual code. But the other thing this
brings up, which I think...
I don't know if this has a real name
anywhere other than in my
mind... but I'm going to say this thing
called the 'philosophy
of incremental development'.
Here's the real reason why programming
is hard, why everything we're gonna do
is going to be challenging and not going
to be just...
you're not going to do it instantly and you're
going to struggle. You have a very very
incredibly powerful
thing in your head, which is your brain.
And you can think about all sorts of
sophisticated systems and ideas and
design ideas and come up with the steps,
the pseudocode,
and understand how stuff works, right?
Maybe you haven't played the game
"Pong" before, but if you have, you kind of
know how it works. You could describe it
to me, you could understand,
you could probably without watching a
single video anymore you could sort
of describe
how to write the computer program
for "Pong".
But actually putting that down into code,
all at once,
is kinda impossible. This idea
that you really need to get used to
is taking an idea like "Pong"...
let's say the project -- and and you're gonna
come up with
hopefully much more interesting and exciting
creative ideas -- the project "Pong"...
Ah, I just realized I forgot to mention all
the stuff in the introductory video, but
I'll figure out how to fit
it in somewhere.
The project "Pong", you wanna break that
down in your head
into lots and lots of mini programs, right?
Here's a mini program for you,
one that draws
a rectangle on the screen. One that moves
the rectangle up and down,
just with the keys,
right? The up and down keys for
example. Another program is one
that just draws a circle in the middle
of the screen, that moves the circle,
that turns the circle around
when it... you need lots and lots
of little pieces. A program that...
um... you can
hava a number appear on the screen that
can go up and down,
maybe randomly. You need to divide "Pong"
into lots and lots...
"Pong" wasn't the best example... but
you want to divide
"Pong" into lots and lots of mini programs,
and make all those mini programs
one at a time. Then you can start to
piece them together.
You can't just sit down, "Do do do do
do do do do do do do...
I'm writing code for an hour or
two.
Finished. Done. Run. Ah, I have "Pong".
You need to make lots and lots
of mini steps, and
accomplish them one at a time. Always run
your program, always make sure it's still
working. Otherwise,
if you write a ton of code,
and then run it and it doesn't work,
where are you... how are you going to know what
went wrong? Right? This idea of making
little incremental changes, taking a
larger problem and breaking down into
smaller pieces,
this is how you going to make stuff. But
this is going to feel wrong to you
because you understand how it all works,
and it's going to seem almost very
kindergarten-esque. Kindergarten is
a wonderful place by the way, we should all just
live in perpetual kindergarten, we'd all be
much happier. I don't mean that in a bad
way, but it's going
to seem like I should be
able to move faster than this.
I should be able to do this more quickly,
with more agility,
but you have to think about it -- this is a
very very flawed
analogy here -- but you think about
learning a new language,
you know, a new foreign language,
you'e not going to pick it up
immediately.
It's going to be a long process, and the
same is true for learning this new
language
of writing code. Okay,
so that's really "What is programming?"
Kinda what is your first
program,
how we're thinking about and how we're going to
approach all these problems
as we begin to write actual examples,
which we're getting to very soon.
The nice thing about this is you can always
just stop and move right to it. I think
the next video was gonna, I'm just going to
talk about different programming
languages,
and this language called Processing, and
why I'm using it in this video series, and what
the pros and cons of that are.
So that will be next.
Whew. Pause