So this third video [inintelligible]
forget about the numbers!
I'll number them,
I can't keep track of anything
[ramble]
but ok, so
I forgot a couple of things
in the previous video that
I'm just gonna kind of fill in right here.
One is, and I think I showed you this
in one of the introductory videos
about Processing but you should take note
of the fact that Processing comes with
a huge amount of examples
So I also encourage you when you're
beginning to just go through
some of these basic examples -
particularly 'form' here
you might kind of like ... well, this actually
has a lot of stuff that we haven't learned yet
but you can get kind of a sense
what is possible to draw in Processing
You might find that useful just to poke
through a bunch of the examples
and see what they do.
The other couple things
I wanted to mention
is that Processing, in addition to having that
reference, that I showed you on the website,
you can also here under 'Help'
if you are not online, you can actually
get the reference by just clicking this,
it's going to open the reference page.
Processing downloads with the reference as well.
So you can actually, from the development
environment itself,
look up stuff in the reference as well.
The last thing that I want to mention is
that you might have noticed
that text is turning different colors.
If I, by accident, delete this 'e',
we can see that the 'lin' is in black
and if I add the 'e' in lowercase it's in blue.
So the Processing development environment
will color the text that you are writing
in different colors just as a little way of
helping you along
to see that you're spelling things right
and what's a known word and what's
an unknown word
but those colors have nothing to do
with how you program executes.
It's just a visual help to see that you've spelled
things wrong.
So one thing that you might notice
when I run this it's gonna say:
'The function lin() does not exist'
because it doesn't exist!
But the function line() does exist in Processing
and I would correct that by typing an 'e'.
Ok ...[ramble] ... back to color!
[ramble]
... so what we've done so far is
we've learned about downloading
Processing, running Processing,
we understand about a computer graphics
window, x-axis, y-axis, where the pixels are,
we got a sense of different functions
we can use to draw to the window
but ... what about color?
So one thing you'll notice
if we go back and run this program -
you'll notice that the line is black,
the rectangle seems to be white but
maybe has a black out line,
and the back of the window itself is just
kind of this grey color.
So we've never specified a single color
for anything. we didn't say
draw a red line,
we didn't say draw a blue line,
we didn't say draw a rectangle
with a blue filling and a red outline.
Processing just decided to use default colors
which you can see are just black and white
because we didn't specify.
but now is the moment that we can start
to look at how to specify colors.
ok, so how do we do that?
So one thing that we should be aware of
is that any shape in Processing,
take a rectangle, for example,
it has both an outline, which we should
really call a 'stroke',
and it has also an interior,
which we will call a 'fill'.
So 'fill' and 'stroke' are the key words,
the function names,
that set color in Processing
for the outline and the interior of a shape.
Now a line has no fill
because a line only has a stroke.
But an ellipse or a rectangle
has both a stroke, the outline, and a fill.
[ramble]
So how does this work?
Let's say that we have a program which draws
a rectangle at 200,150, with
a width of 50, and a height of 35 pixels.
So this is our program that we are writing.
...maybe kind of erase this.
How do we set that rectangle's color?
The way we set a shape's color
is by setting the fill or stroke
with the lines of code
in advance of saying 'rect()'
So the order of operations really matters!
What we're doing is almost like
the Processing program is running
and there's like a thing with a pen there
and it reads:
Oh, uhm, stroke blue! Oh, quick,
let me go get a blue pen!
or a red one. Whenever I get to rect()
I will draw it with red.
And if it says 'stroke black' it'll
suddenly switch and get the black pen again!
So it's reading the code step by step
and setting the stroke, setting the fill,
for whatever that next shape
is going to be.
So if I were to say: stroke ...
We need some arguments, right?
How do we define the arguments for a color?
...and we need a fill.
So that's a big question!
We can see that what we're ultimately
going to do is we might say:
Hey, I wanna have some sort of
color - stroke - for the line,
and some sort of stroke,
and some sort of fill,
for that rectangle, right?
I wanna give the line a stroke,
the rectangle a stroke and a fill.
But what are those arguments?
What are those arguments?
How do we define color?
[ramble]
So first of all there are lots of ways
to think about color.
You might, sometime in your life,
have done finger-painting,
and you had like some primary colors
and you could mix them,
and get others colors,
that's a nice way to start thinking!
So that's kind of what we're going to do,
but we are not going to use those ...
[ramble]
We're going to mix colors,
but we're going to mix digital color
and digital color follows
the properties of light.
So we need a little bit of red -
some amount of red,
some amount of green,
and some amount of blue.
and all of those together will give us a color!
So that's what we're going to do.
So we need three arguments,
and this is what's known as RGB color.
[ramble]
I wanna mention that we're not gonna
get into all of this right now, but
Processing allows you to
define color in many ways.
You can define color based on
something called
hue, saturation, brightness.
You can define color with all sorts of
different amounts of ranges,
but what we're going to look at
is the default way that color works,
it's the best way to get started and kind of just
try stuff out, although I think that
looking at hue, saturation, brightness
is kind of important.
That's probably its own video though.
The default way is, again,
red, green and blue.
So the ranges for each one
of these values is 0 to 255.
So if we say '0 red'
then that's NO red.
If we say '255 red'
that's A LOT of red, right?
So you can imagine what is this color -
0,255,0
if this is, again, RGB color
and we're saying the fill
what would this color be?
No red, no blue, but turn
the green switch all the way on!
So that's a green color, right?
Let's go take a look at that,
to just prove that this works.
If I make the interior of this
rectangle green
and the stroke of the rectangle
I'm going to say is red
and I'm gonna have the stroke of the line,
just so that we see all three of these,
as blue, and we run it again
we can see now:
aha, we have a green rectangle
with a red outline and a blue line.
Why? we have all of that because
that's what we specified
with stroke:
0 red, 0 green, 255 blue, right?
So obviously,
this is just sort of a very basic
beginning of this,
and you might start to mix colors,
and imagine: what does
green and red make
for the fill of that rectangle?
Yellow!
So I'm a little color-challenged
[ramble]
but I have a feeling that if you
found your way here
you're interested in design,
maybe you have some ideas yourself.
So what I would say here is this is
kind of all I have ... in terms of color
I would encourage you to
start playing around.
You might have experience using Photoshop,
or designing websites,
and you've done a lot of stuff
with color already.
Processing actually, by the way, also allows you,
this is a bit of a digression,
to write your colors this way,
so if you've ever done color for
the web with this hexadecimal notation,
you can also do that directly in Processing.
But I think I want to focus, really,
primarily on this idea of numbers:
red, green, blue.
but ...
let me add, we're only at 6 or so minutes,
let me add a few more things
to this equation.
First of all, what if I
were to make the fill
255,255,255?
All the way red, all the way green,
all the way blue.
What do you think you gonna get?
- jeopardy music playing -
you can run it and you're going to see
we have a white rectangle!
again, remember this is the properties of light,
so if we take all of red, all of green
and all of blue,
mix them together then we have white light!
If we turn all the lights off,
if every one of these values
is 0: 0,0,0 then we have black.
So we only have color
in all those sort of areas inbetween,
so to speak
so one thing that I should say
is that
if you want to do white, right?
we said it's fill(255,255,255);
or black: (0,0,0);
Processing allows you to do something
with a little bit of shorthand,
it would be very inconvenient to always
have to put all three in there
So if you ever specify color
with one argument
instead of three, it will assume
what you meant to do was
to use that number for all three values.
so I can say:
[ramble]
I can say fill(255);
instead of fill(255,255,255);
and get the same result:
a white rectangle.
Which is interesting to note
because, by the way,
what if I say:
fill(100); ?
Notice I have a grey color, a dark grey,
not black, because 0 would be black,
it turns out that greyscale color,
by the way,
anything greyscale color
is a color where red = green = blue.
So (100,100,100) is
a slightly dark grey
that we could give a shorthand
as just the argument '100'.
So we can both specify color as
a single value for a greyscale color,
or three values for red, green and blue.
Two more things I wanna touch on
in this video:
[ramble]
So the other thing I wanna mention is
by the way,
there is a function called background()
which allows me to also set the color
for the background.
So there is a black background
which I did using a single argument,
for greyscale
or, I could say: 0,255,0
and here's a green background
with that color.
So the background() function
fills in the background
of your Processing sketch window
with a color.
Now the other thing I should just
mention by the way
is I have been using the word 'program',
your 'application',
the 'Processing window',
'sketch', I wanna try to now consistently
use the word 'sketch'.
The word 'sketch' is kind of a word for
a Processing program
we think of this, sort of folder
of Processing programs
as your sketchbook,
for this idea that
one of the things that Processing
allows you to do
is very quickly sketch out ideas
through code.
So I'm just gonna say
your Processing sketch
now has a green background!
However here is something really important!
Order of operations is key, right?
Just because, what is background
actually doing?
It fills the screen with a single color!
Even though we think of the term
'background' as if it should
put it behind everything
but the order that this code executes
is quite important!
What if I were to put
background at the end?
What do you think is gonna happen?
Will it look the same?
Clearly no!
Otherwise why would I be doing this?
Look what happens: I don't see my
rectangle and line anymore.
Because it drew those lines,
drew the rectangle,
but then it drew the background
on top of it!
Once we start doing animation,
this idea of where the background goes
is going to be truly, truly key.
Ok, the other thing I should just
point out, by the way,
is that if I didn't set a stroke for
this second rectangle, the stroke,
... of course, the background
at the end
the stroke from the line
will carry over,
which is very hard for you to see,
but I can zoom in
You can see that both the line and
(the border of) the rectangle are blue
that's because, remember when we set
the stroke, it's the stroke value
for all shapes that are drawn afterwards
unless you override that stroke
with a new value.
I should also just point out:
look how I am typing this,
the actual, these extra line breaks,
and where I put the stroke and the fill,
none of that really matters!
I like to put these in little groups
cause I'm an obsessive coder who's like
ok, let me put size() and background() together,
then stroke() and line()
then stroke(), fill() and rect()
I can read it, it makes sense
but ... truly, none of that matters
in fact this code
would execute exactly the same way,
but it's much harder to read!
because the line breaks
don't matter at all.
Semicolon is what tells the Processing
program we've reached the end of a line.
..
So what is important to realize,
is that the syntax, spaces and linebreaks,
tend to not really matter, right?
I could put a lot of spaces here,
oops, I put this extra stuff,
it's actually gonna run exactly
the same way.
but there often is a way
of writing code
that feels a little bit more
human readable
[ramble]
I'm gonna do a couple more things
in this video
and maybe I'll fix these later,
through some magic way of doing it again
with better editing, or something,
but, ok, so that's what I
wanted to mention there
ok, the other thing,
[ramble]
So here's the other thing,
there is something you can
put in your code
which, in a way, like, doesn't count.
if I ever typed: '//' you can see
suddenly this line is like a light grey
and I can say: this will draw
a green rectangle
and I can run this program
and it still runs.
This is what is known as a
'code comment'
If you ever wanna write annotations
in your code,
You might do something like:
// TODO: fix this line,
I don't like the design
you could add comments to yourself
in the code
something that you might
wanna do later,
just explanations of what different
sections of the code are doing.
Right now I feel silly to be doing this,
because it's so short and obvious
what's happening, although
you know, these functions
and numbers are somewhat cryptic,
but your future self will
thank your present self later
if you get into the habit of
writing comments into your code now,
because it inevitably will happen
that you work on a program
for quite a while
you will go on vacation
or do something else
that has nothing to do
with sitting hunched over your computer,
cause that's good for you,
and when you come back to it
you're not going to remember
how it works or what you wanna look at
and instead -- but if you have all
those code comments in there
it will allow you to get back
into it more easily.
So get into the habit of doing that now.
So we kind of have reached the end
of this first of three videos here:
One, talking about coordinate systems,
one looking at Processing and
starting to write code,
now we saw a little bit about color
I'm gonna give you two hints
of things that you could look at
and maybe I will fill them back in
and practice with another video later.
There is a function called colorMode()
that I would encourage you to look up
in the reference
it's like an exercise:
look up 'colorMode' in the reference.
What are some examples?
Can you change the colorMode
and define colors differently?
One color mode that you can
do in Processing
is HSB for hue, saturation, brightness
sometimes it's written as HSV,
hue, saturation, value
but this is another way of defining
color that's different
than RGB: hue being the color on the
colorwheel, what is the hue of a color?
Is it greenish? Blue? Is it really blue?
Is it really red?
Saturation being 'how vibrant is the color?'
And brightness being 'how bright
is that color?'
Is it a very dark blue or
a really bright blue?
So one way you can play with
designing colors is
hue, saturation, brightness
and you can affect that with the colorMode()
The other thing that I
totally didn't mention at all
We said that fill could have one argument,
which would be a greyscale color
We said that fill could have three arguments,
which would be an RGB color
Well here's two other amounts of arguments
that fill can have:
Fill could have 2 arguments,
which is greyscale + transparency
It could also have 4 arguments:
which is RGB + transparency,
often written as 'alpha',
the alpha value.
An 'alpha' of 0 means
completely transparent
An 'alpha' of 255 means
completely opaque
Now of course there is no such thing
as real transparency.
It's not that suddenly your physical screen
will be see-through
It is this idea of creating
the illusion of transparency,
So if you draw a color with no transparency
you will see that color literally
on the screen, if you draw a color with
some transparency, it will
look like it blends through.
and I know that I said that
I wasn't really going to
go through this in great detail
but let's actually just look at this
for a second ... let's make this rectangle
much, much wider,
so that we can see it
This is our,
we have a green background
I'm gonna give this a black background,
so it's a little bit easier to see,
oh, that was not the fill.
let's have a nice, bright green rectangle
which we can see right here
What if we were to draw
another rectangle on top
which is red
and we'll do it 150, 50, with 100 pixels
wide and 300 pixels high, right?
Look at that. See that red rectangle
right on top of that green rectangle?
Right, that's 100% opaque.
But what if we give it a little bit
of transparency?
0 is completely transparent,
255 is completely opaque,
so 127 will be right in the middle there,
like 50%,
if we do this, look, we can see,
ah, the camera shut off ...
[ramble]
You can see now that there is red here
that is blending with the black behind it
and the red here is blending
with the green behind it.
Blending being, it's almost like it's a
tinted lens that we put on top there.
So, of course, this opens up another
can of worms,
There are many different ways
of blending colors
this is an infinite world of
stuff you can look at and do
all of this is contained in the reference
and ... examples and
through trial and error
but this is to give you some beginning steps
to get started.
So I think in a way you have
all the tools now
you have all the tools
to make a first design
you know about the coordinate system,
you know about basic shapes,
and you know about color.
so make yourself an alien,
my little example that I always use
is like this tiny little thing, person, alien
whatever you call it, Zoog,
You can see there are some ellipses,
some rectangles and some lines
you design something, share it,
send it to me,
You're gonna start to want to use arcs,
and curves and triangles,
Doing this will force you to dig into
the Processing reference a bit more.
So I have one more video in this little sequence
which is about some other advanced
drawing functions in Processing,
to do more complex shapes
which I think I will tack
on at some point,
but this is the first week or time
or whatever , that's your exercise.
Ok, thank you,
this video is way too long!
I should probably cut it into
a few different ones but
it is what it is right now.
I'm going to have something to eat
[ramble]
See yourself later and I hope
you are enjoying yourself and your day!
Bye!